Let me show you this app that I just
spun up using instrumental components.
It only took like four commands. So,
here's a preview of instrumental
components, which is launching very
soon. Here's the finished app, and then
I'll show you how I did it in just four
commands. I scaffolded up a model for
guitars. I can list out um each guitar.
It's got these uh drop-own menus. It's
got a system for adding a new guitar and
editing each guitar. As you can see, we
have uh breadcrumbs up there. Up here
I've got my uh user navigation where I
can manage my account settings. I can
even see all of my team members. So I
can invite team members, they can accept
invitations, I can create a new
invitation and I can uh you know
personalize it. Give each person a role.
I can even switch accounts. So I have
multiple accounts here. I can use this
account switcher up here to easily
switch between my two accounts. And I
even have a back office admin area. Uses
a different color scheme. And here I can
see all of the users who've signed up
for my app. I can see all the accounts
that were created. And when I install
our instrumental commerce component, I
can manage all of my products and
subscriptions and purchases all here in
the back end. I can go into any user and
I can even impersonate the user to uh
you know run some customer support and
and seeing what's happening in their
account. And I can stop impersonating
right here and come right back into my
admin dashboard. All of it is
customizable. And so now I've got all
the table stakes installed in my new
product here. And now all I need to do
is start adding my core features and I'm
off and running. So let me tear all this
down and let's rebuild it in just a
couple of commands using instrumental
components. Okay, so I've just started
over. I've got a fresh Rails app. The
only thing that I've added so far is the
Rails 8 authentication generator. And
all that did was it gave me a basic
signin flow. So let's start using
instrumental components to get this
thing ready for prime time. First thing
I want to do is add our authentication
component, which is a layer on top of
the Rails authentication, and it gives
user profiles, a sign up and
registration flow, user avatars, a panel
for users to manage their profiles.
We're going to do Rails instrumental
authentication. First, it's going to
check some requirements to make sure
that we have the basics already
installed, and we do. Then, it's going
to give me a preview. This one pulls in
14 other components from instrumental in
the things that are about to be
installed. So, we've got the logo
component, uh, user menu, drop downs,
flash forms, tool tips, buttons, icons,
subnavs, avatars, breadcrumbs. So, um,
let's get all that installed in one
shot. I'm going to proceed. But before
we actually get into it, it's going to
ask a couple of questions about what I
want to do. We want to make that our
default layout. So, I'll approve that. I
can choose which icons library I want to
use. I like to use Font Awesome. Okay,
so now we are off to the races. We're
going to now automatically install all
of these components directly into the
project itself. So, as you can see, you
could watch the progress here. It's
adding files. It's adding controllers,
views, partials, stimulus controllers,
TWIN CSS styling. Um, it's it's adding
functionality and wire wiring things up
so that it all just works right out of
the box, but it is putting these files
directly in your project so that you can
fully customize everything and
everything is documented over at
instrumental.dev. I can watch this
progress happen or I can use fast mode
and all this stuff will install
instantly. But we'll fast forward a
little bit here.
Okay, so we have completed that
installation and right here it gives us
a little recap to sort of run down
everything that happened. So we've added
77 new files right into our project.
Here's the list. Uh we've also inserted
code into some existing files, keeping
their existing code intact and just
adding a few methods, helpers, some
styling and whatnot. Um, this one did
include one new migration, so it's
giving us a reminder. We'll go ahead and
do
that. And we also added some new routes.
We'll take a look at those in in a
minute. Let's see how we're doing so
far. So, here's our new login screen.
Much cleaner. It's all responsive. It's
uh it uses our our form styling, our
button styling. We also have a signup
form now. We have some social proof on
there. All of this, of course, is
customizable. Um, but you know, before I
go ahead and register for a new account,
I want to make sure that we have our
accounts system and teams and and user
system all squared away. So, we're going
to add the instrumental teams
component. Rails instrumental teams. And
so, what this is going to do is it's
going to add a couple more components.
And then it's also using a bunch of
components that we already have
installed in our project. It detected
that. So, we're good to go. So, I'm
going to proceed with
this. And so, this is going to uh wire
up our uh team member invitation system,
a bunch of mailers for that, the way to
track invitations and uh and being able
to manage and different roles for
different users in our
accounts. All right, here is the recap
of that one. We've got all the files
here and everything that happened. And
by the way, we also have all this
information stored in log instrumental.
It gives you all the details of what
exactly was installed, which components
were installed and which files were
added. So you always have a record of
everything that was added into your
project for you. So you're in complete
control to manage and customize every
single detail of what instrumental does.
And now let's go ahead and actually sign
up for an account. Okay, so now we're
logged in. We've got our flash message.
It disappears there. It's using our
minimal uh layout by default. And we've
got our user profile and settings team
member system all here. But you know
what? Let's upgrade the layout a little
bit. I want this sidebar to be
collapsible. I'm going to run rails gin
instrumental
layout. We're going to use collapsible
sidebar. All right. I'm going to refresh
the server. And now we have a sidebar
which can collapse. That's pretty cool.
It even remembers the state that I leave
it in. Pretty cool. All right. So now
let's start adding some features. I want
to scaffold out uh a model. So I'm going
to go ahead and run rails g
instrumental scaffold. Let's do guitars.
I'll give each one a name. We need a
brand color strings integer uh
purchased daytime. That's good enough.
We're going to proceed and get this
stuff built out. So, a couple uh
questions up front as it customizes how
the guitars model and views are going to
be integrated into our project. Which
one defines its name? I do want to
generate unique slugs for each guitar in
the collection. I do want to pageionate
the uh index view and yeah, it's going
to get all that stuff wired up and
installed into the project. Okay, so
there we go. I'm going to migrate that.
Okay, we don't have any guitars yet.
Even this little thing here is a little
component for when we don't have any
records, but let's go ahead and add the
first
guitar. And I can, you know, add more
fields to it. This is uh just very basic
kind of boilerplate stuff. We've got our
drop down all built in. Um, this is our
listings component. By the way,
everything, of course, is mobile
optimized. We've got a a mobile uh menu
all built in. And everything is dark
mode ready as well. Let's go to my team
members. I just want to uh demo the uh
user
invitation. I can give the person a
role. I'll send that invitation. It
sends the invite as a mailer. The
mailers are all wired up. I can accept
that and open up in a different browser.
And so now I'm joining this team. It
says I've been invited to join. I can
set my password. I've logged in and it
also notified the person who sent the
invitation. So all of that stuff is
wired up and ready to go. In my main
account, I can track the status of each
invitation and I can look at the list of
my team members. Pretty cool. I think
the last piece is to add that admin
backend dashboard. We're going to do
Rails
instrumental. You guessed it, admin.
Okay, the admin has been installed.
We're going to uh add that one column to
the user table. And I'm going to have to
go directly into the database and set
this user as the super admin for the
app. So I've done that. And so now this
user gets a special link called admin. I
can click that takes me into the admin
dashboard. It's using the secondary
color scheme. Um, all of that is
customizable in the Tailwind CSS
settings that you have directly in your
codebase. Um, here you can see each of
your users, the accounts. I can look at
a user, I can impersonate the user. Um,
and uh, all of this stuff is just wired
up and ready to go. And as I add more
features to my app, I can manage them
here in the admin s such as instrumental
commerce where I can uh manage purchases
and subscriptions and payments with uh
the users for my product. All of that
can be managed here in the back end. So
I'm back into my app and that is a quick
look at instrumental components. You can
get on the early access list at
instrumental.dev. Any questions or
feedback, let me know. The